טוב Tov so we start today and we're in the בבלי Bavli
and we start today on דף י"ח daf yud chet in the
beginning of the second
פרק. perek. And as I said I was mentioning before that we
recorded I recorded the דף daf for תשעה באב Tisha B'Av yesterday
so that's online. And there were just two interesting things that did
come up one in the בבלי Bavli one in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
because it was dealing with the issue of the סנהדרין גדולה. Sanhedrin
Gedolah.
So it dealt with the issue about
first of all to be on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin you need to
be able to speak other languages in order so that you can
hear directly the testimony of the witnesses and of the litigants without
an interpreter. Obviously very important to be able to not concern yourself
that you're missing some even if not conscious misrepresentation some issue of
nuance or emphasis or whatever. But also the בבלי Bavli dealt with
this idea which is very famous that somebody's not able to be
on a בית דין Beis Din unless they can figure out a
way to argue that a שרץ sheretz is טהור. tahor. And תוספות
Tosfos famously asks like מה לנו לדרשות של הבל mah lanu ledrashot
shel hevel like why is that supposed to be an important thing
to demonstrate that you can be on the בית דין? Beis Din?
So obviously to some degree it's to demonstrate intellectual prowess that you
can prove a
counterfactual conclusion but the question but what it also raises is that
it's not all about intellect. You can have very smart people right
and you can so what's to prove that the integrity of a
decision right if you have enough brains you know and you know
the texts well enough you can come up to any conclusion you
want to. I was actually just reading in the I think it
was the New York Times or somewhere no maybe the New Yorker
anyway a review about a young woman who like she was number
one on the continent
in debating you know and like as a college student or whatever
she won all these debate things and then she basically felt that
it was like morally draining for her because she had to argue
all these positions that were like you know morally dubious and that
she couldn't identify with. And you're able to win a debate if
you can make a good enough argument right? So anyway so she
left the whole thing and now she came out with a novel
anyway that was the point of the review they love her novel
but the point is is like it's like you know you can
argue devil quoting scriptures. So which interesting to note that if you
look at the at the criteria for who can serve on the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin both in the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi what
really jumps up at you is not intellectual ability and is not
knowledge but is character issues about the quality of a person's character
you know their
humility their probity you know their integrity and so on. And I
think that's a really important thing you know because it's true even
up until today for פוסקים poskim and so on people can come
up with any conclusion that you want in theory you know and
how do you really know that you know how can you really
trust a decision a lot of that really had to do with
somebody's integrity
and fidelity and יראת שמים yiras shamayim and so on. So that's
an important thing to underscore. And the other thing I'll just mention
is that in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it dealt with this famous תוספתא
Tosefta a very large תוספתא Tosefta about how there used to never
be any
debate because they would always refer everything up to a higher בית
דין Beis Din until the סנהדרין Sanhedrin until you had the students
of הלל ושמאי Hillel and Shammai who did not attend to their
rabbis appropriately and that led to all of these debates. So we'll
see this later in the בבלי Bavli but the one thing that
I just should mention and people should listen to the recording is
that what really emerged from there is you know and it says
if a בית דין Beis Din didn't know something they went to
the next higher בית דין. Beis Din. אם שמעו אמרו להם Im
shamu amru lahem ואם לא שמעו ve-im lo shamu they went to
the next higher בית דין. Beis Din. And then when it got
to the סנהדרין Sanhedrin it says אם שמעו אמרו להם im shamu
amru lahem ואם לא שמרו ve-im lo shamru עמדו למנין. amdu leminyan.
If they knew they told them if they had a tradition and
if they didn't have a tradition they took a vote and what
it never says anywhere in that entire process is if they didn't
have a tradition they tried to figure it out for themselves like
they actually used their own creativity and analysis it never says that.
And that really like represents this idea that there was never a
debate and we always knew exactly what the הלכה halacha was but
it also represents a particular model of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al
peh which is it's all just transmission it's all just everything that
we've been given and handing it down and debate is a bad
thing because debate means that
you don't know what the tradition says about something that there's uncertainty
right and that's a very and therefore you know and therefore it's
praising this period when there was never any debate when we had
a good hold on all the details of what the tradition had
to say. Okay but that's very different I think than a lot
of you know sort of if you want to say the הלל
Hillel or the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva models of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh
which is that any tradition any text is inherently limited and is
not going to have the you know be able to answer every
question that's going to come up in the future and debate emerges
from the fact that you apply your human intellect and creativity to
understand something and number one not only is it natural but two
it's good because it opens up a space for multiple opinions and
for creativity and development and so on. So it's worth sort of
thinking about that in terms of that model there and we will
see the same תוספתא Tosefta discussed at length in the בבלי Bavli
as well but that's just very interesting about you know when
you. So it's a very different type of a model. Yeah. Okay.
Alright, yes, רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ismael.
It doesn't know, it's just like anonymous, it doesn't attribute it to
anybody. The one that she read. Oh, it's more רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer and maybe a בית שמאי Beit Shammai pro רבי אליעזר, Rebbe
Eliezer, never said anything he didn't hear from his רבי Rebbe and
so on. Anyway, so that's some of the stuff we covered, well,
not on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, but we pre-recorded for because we
did not give a דף Daf on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So
now we're going to start with the second פרק, perek, כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. So we move from like one of the things that's
interesting, which are the things that the, you know, that the, here,
the narrative sort of of the major theme digresses from. Like one
thing bizarre nobody sort of stopped to ask, I don't know the
answer, but like in the previous משנה Mishnah where it dealt with
all the different sizes of the בית דין, Beit Din, it had
a digression about the issue of עיר הנדחת, Ir Nidachat, don't do
three in a row, do you do it on a border city?
Like, why are we talking about that? We're not dealing with עיר.
Ir. I mean, it was, you know, just in passing a mention
about the size of the בית דין, Beis Din, right? It had
a little bit of a digression about although he, about the question
about like, you know, a serpent or a lion that kills and
how many do you, but that at least is relevant to the
question of the size of the בית דין. Beis Din. So why
is it with עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachat in that משנה Mishnah from
the first פרק perek is unclear. Here in the second פרק, perek,
also because we mentioned that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is judged
with a בית דין Beis Din of seventy-one, we're going to focus
a little bit on the issue of כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
מלך. Melech. It's, it's a little bit of a digression but not
really so much because if you think about it, it's dealing with
the question about like is anybody above the law? You know, and
who sort of are the types of people that have special treatment
under the law? So it's not really such a digression, although there'll
be elements that will be, as we'll see. So let's take a
look. כהן גדול דן ודנין אותו. Kohen Gadol dan vedanin oto. כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol can be in a בית דין Beis Din and
he can be judged. Now, as we saw from the previous פרק,
perek, when he is judged it's with a בית דין Beis Din
of seventy-one. כל הדבר הגדול יביאו אליך. Kol hadavar hagadol yavi'u eilecha.
That one of like, one of like the leaders of the people,
they get a special בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, but nevertheless he
is judged, he's not above the law. מעיד ומעידין אותו. Me'id ume'idin
oto. He can testify and you can testify against him, which probably
is pretty obvious if he comes to a court case and can
be judged, you're going to be able to have to accept testimony
against him. חולץ וחולצין לאשתו. Choletz vecholtzin le'ishto. Here's where again it
seems to digress a little. Okay, he can be involved in a
חליצה, chalitzah,
and even though that would require that the woman spit at him,
right, his sister-in-law, and if he dies, his wife can be involved
in a חליצה chalitzah with his brother.
ומיבמין את אשתו. Umeyabmim et ishto. Now if he dies, his brother
can do ייבום yibum with his wife. אבל הוא אינו מיבם. Aval
hu eino meyabem. But if his brother dies he can't do ייבום
yibum with his wife's, with his brother's wife, מפני שהוא אסור באלמנה.
mipnei shehu asur be'almanah. Because he's prohibited to marry an אלמנה, almanah,
which of course raises the question then why does he have to
do חליצה chalitzah if he's not able to do ייבום, yibum, right?
He should just think that he should be categorically excluded. Yes.
Is his brother a כהן? Kohen?
But not a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. A כהן Kohen is forbidden
with a גרושה, gerushah, and a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is the
only one forbidden with an אלמנה, almanah, contrary to what יחזקאל Yechezkel
says. The פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel says that a כהן Kohen
can't marry an אלמנה, almanah, but that's not the הלכה. halachah. That's
one of the places where they found יחזקאל Yechezkel סותר דברי תורה.
soter divrei Torah. Okay. The הלכה halachah is that a כהן Kohen
can marry an אלמנה, almanah, not a גרושה. gerushah. So anyway, so
his brother, he can do, his brother can do ייבום yibum for
his wife, but he can't do ייבום yibum for his brother's wife.
מת לו מת. Mes lo met. Now if an immediate relative dies,
אינו יוצא אחר המיטה. eino yotzei achar hamitah. He can, he does
not directly follow the coffin, אלא הן נכנסין והוא נגלה. ela hen
nichnasim vehu nigleh.
When they let's say turn a street then he appears on the
street that they just turned away from, הן נגלין והוא נכסה. hen
niglin vehu nichseh. When they appear on a street, he, he's like
hides himself from that street. He's never visible on the same street.
He's always following them at a distance. ויוצא עמהן עד פתח שער
העיר. Veyotzei iman ad petach sha'ar ha'ir. But he,
so in this way by sort of keeping at a distance and
so on, he accompanies the, you know, the coffin till it gets
to the gates of the city, because it's being brought out of
the city to be buried in the graveyard outside of the city.
דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. That's obviously to protect himself so he doesn't accidentally become טמא.
tamei. Because even though a normal כהן Kohen is allowed and even
has a מצוה mitzvah to be מטמא mitamei to his immediate relatives,
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not allowed. לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא
להם במותם. Le'aviv ule'imo lo yitama lahem bemotam. I keep on getting,
I keep on misquoting whether it's the פסוקים pesukim from the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol or the נזיר, nazir, because anyway, they're the same,
basically the same הלכה, halachah, which is that he is not מטמא
mitamei to his immediate, immediate relatives, right? So let's just find it
quickly, it's in the beginning of אמור. Emor.
There.
והכהן הגדול מאחיו. V'hakohen hagadol
me'echav. One minute. והכהן
הגדול מאחיו אשר יוצק על ראשו שמן המשחה
ומלא את ידו ללבש את
הבגדים את ראשו לא יפרע ובגדיו לא יפרם,
Ve'hacohen hagadol me'achav asher yutzak al rosho shemen hamishcha u'milei et yado
lilbosh et habegadim et rosho lo yifra u'vegadav
lo yifrom,
so when he becomes a
mourner, he cannot let his hair grow wild or rent his garment.
ועל כל נפשות מת לא יבא לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא. Ve'al kol
nafshot met lo yavo le'aviv u'le'imo lo yitama.
Okay, so he cannot become טמא tamei even to his immediate relatives,
alright. And then it says, אלמנה וגרושה חללה זונה, Almana u'grusha chalala
zona, so he can't marry an אלמנה almana and so on. Okay,
so that's what he's not allowed to do as opposed to a
normal כהן, kohen, so he has to keep his distance. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, it's more than just keeping your distance, אינו
יוצא מן המקדש. eino yotzei min hamikdash.
He does not leave the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, משום שנאמר ומן
המקדש לא יצא, mishum shene'emar u'min hamikdash lo yetzei, a very literal
read of the פסוק. pasuk. ומן המקדש לא יצא, U'min hamikdash lo
yetzei, he keeps on doing the עבודה avoda even after, even when
his relative died, his mother or father died, he's still in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash even as they're taking the coffin out to
be buried. Okay, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it, we'll see
in the, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is going to read that מן
הקדושה לא יצא, min hakedusha lo yetzei, like he cannot risk his
קדושה, kedusha, but it doesn't mean he can't literally leave the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is reading it very
literal, he has to keep on working in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. וכשהוא מנחם אחרים, U'keshehu menachem acherim, now when he is giving
consolation to others who have suffered a loss, דרך כל העם עוברים
זה אחר זה, derech kol ha'am ovrim ze achar ze, so you
know what we do is we have שתי שורות shtei shurot after
the
burial of המנחמים hamenachamim and the mourners walk between and everybody says
המקום ינחם אתכם. HaMakom yenachem etchem. But here it's describing a scenario
which is sort of like the flip, which is sort of like
the mourner stands and everybody passes
through. Sometimes like in some places they have that like everybody passes
in front and shakes hands with the רב rav or the נשיא
nasi or whoever as a greeting. Here it's like where the person
who is the mourner is standing in a place and people are
in a row coming by and wishing them נחמה. nechama. So when
he is מנחם אחרים, menachem acherim, דרך כל העם
עוברים זה אחר זה, derech kol ha'am ovrim ze achar ze, everybody's
sort of going in a line, והממונה ממוצע בינו לבין העם, ve'hamemuna
memutza beino levein ha'am, and the ממונה, memuna, his like his second
in command, his vice כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he's sort of stands
between him and the rest of the people. He's like a buffer
between him and the people and allows him to pass in front
of the mourner.
רש"י Rashi says what that means is that the ממונה memuna then
is on his right and the people are on his left. That's
וכשהוא מתנחם מאחרים. u'keshehu mitnachem me'acherim.
Now if he is the one receiving consolers, he is the mourner,
so כל העם אומרים לו אנו כפרתך. kol ha'am omrim lo anu
kaparat'cha. Everybody says to them we will be your atonement, let whatever
bad that should happen to you let it happen to us but
us serve in your stead to atone for any sins, which obviously
reflects an idea that if a somebody died it was perceived of
as this tragedy was somehow as a result of the person's
sins and that's sort of so they're saying let any bad thing,
I mean this person obviously already suffered the loss, but let any
future bad thing happen to you happen to us. It's also interesting
that when after somebody has died, the, you know, what's sort of
directly connected to this is what the גמרא Gemara sort of says
is that you're supposed to say like sort of in the period
after the death is הריני כפרת משכבו. hareini kaparat mishkavo. Let I
like if somebody's let's say father died, mother died, says let I
be the, I should be the atonement for their, you know, for
that person,
for my, which means like let
bad things happen to me so that it atones for them and
that their soul is able to merit the afterlife. So it's a
similar type of a sort of a theology. Here you've suffered a
death, means that some there's some sins that have to be paid
for,
whether it's the sins of the one who passed away and therefore
the surviving relative says let me be atoned for their sins, let
bad things happen to me is presumably what it means, or you
could say it in a more positive way that I hope through
the through the good deeds that I do, like that's the more
way we think about it, that you sort of do good deeds,
you learn משניות, Mishnayot, you do other things and those bring about
atonement for the soul, but it's that the deceased needs atonement, or
it's that maybe the reason that this death happened is that this
person's sins brought, because that's a way of thinking about it, you
this person suffered the loss so something he needs atonement, and let
us sort of be your atonement, which is what is being said
here, אנו כפרתך. anu kaparat'cha. והוא אומר להם תתברכו מן השמים, Ve'hu
omer lahem titvarchu min hashamayim, you should be blessed from heaven. וכשהוא
מברין אותו, U'keshehu mavrin oto, now when he is being given console,
הבראה havara is the meal served to the mourner right after he
comes back from the burial, כל העם מסובין על הארץ והוא מיסב
על הספסל, kol ha'am mesubin al ha'aretz ve'hu meisev al hasafsal, as
opposed to the normal thing where the mourner would be on the
ground and everybody else would be on a chair, here because of
the honor to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, that they
are actually they are on the ground and it's sort of similar
to אנו כפרתך, anu kaparat'cha, like let us sort of be share
in your mourning, let us sort of be... In your stead, be
the ones who are suffering in your stead as it were. So
they actually are the ones that sit on the ground and he,
because he's the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he's actually higher than them.
So it's a little bit of a reversal. Okay, so that's about
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and this is the part obviously so
the part about the judging and the witness bearing witness is directly
relevant. This part about the death is a bit of a digression.
המלך לא דן ולא דנין אותו, Hamelech lo dan velo danin oto,
the king does not judge and is not judged. I actually misstated,
somewhat misstated when we learned it before כל הדבר הגדול יביאו אליך,
kol hadavar hagadol yavi’u eleicha, that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
judged by a בית דין Beis Din of 71. I think at
the time I said like a base a king, a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and a king. He would be the obvious גדול. gadol.
Okay, this obviously I think I was a little bit probably subconsciously
influenced by my by my American or whatever Western approach that nobody
is above the law. So I wanted to throw in the king
there, maybe also just for symmetry. But actually if you remember the
גמרא Gemara said that it would include the head of a tribe,
but interestingly how it says a שבט shevet means 71, but what
was absent from that earlier discussion was a king. And this משנה
mishnah actually says that a king is not judged, is somewhat, you
know, higher than the law. Of course it's so ironic because the
תורה, Torah, you know, is all about that he carries a ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, ולא יסור לבבו מאחיו, velo yasur levavo mei'achav, right,
and then he always keeps, you know, it says that he's always
under the law of the תורה, Torah, obviously he's bound by the
law of the תורה. Torah. So this is a little, you know,
troubling that he's not included in this. The גמרא Gemara actually will
say that this only applies to מלכי ישראל Malchei Yisrael because the
מלכי ישראל Malchei Yisrael who were not seen as good kings, and
were seen as less submitting to תורה Torah law. So then you
don't want to judge them because it's only going to be bad
to the you know, to the court system if they tried to
apply, you know, you know, get the kings to serve to come
to court. But then the גמרא's Gemara going to actually say this
does not apply to מלכי יהודה. Malchei Yehuda. So it's interesting. So
therefore I wasn't totally wrong before. But anyway, but from the simple
presentation of this משנה, mishnah, the king is excluded from being able
to be brought to court. המלך לא דן ולא דנין אותו. Hamelech
lo dan velo danin oto. He does not judge but he also
doesn't sit on a court, which is I guess at least a
balance as well, you know as opposed to all the cases where,
you know, they had like, you know in England even, right, they
had two sets of court systems. They had the what was it?
Not civil law, but anyway, there was like one court system was
sort of like the courts and then there was another court system
which was ultimately like the king's court, right? I mean and throughout
the Middle Ages you sort of had this and I imagine even
earlier, right, you'd appeal directly to the king, you know, the king
sort of represented this type of an authority that was not as
much was more at his complete discretion. Look I mean even in
the States, right, you know the president can issue pardons and so
on. So here you had you know so there's something at least
if the king isn't being judged, there's also something I think that's
good about him not judging, not representing a complete system that operates
outside of a law. The court system you know just the king
is not a part of the court system.
Okay, לא דן ולא דנין אותו, lo dan velo danin oso, לא
מעיד ולא מעידין אותו. lo me'id velo me'idin oso. He cannot testify
and you can't testify against him. לא חולץ ולא חולצין, lo choletz
velo choltzin, right you have that in nowadays right there's some people
who you cannot bring as a witness unless they sort of allow
themselves to be called as a witness to be subpoenaed, right, no?
Aren't there maybe it has to do with issues that relate to
national security? But I don't know, if I had a case against
you and I thought that the president you know had actually had
relevant testimony to the case, could I subpoena the president? Would he
be forced to come? I don't think so. I think certain people
of office have to like allow themselves to be called, right, that
they can sort of they can they can claim privilege or something.
That's actually not clear. Really? The courts are kind of wrestling with
that.
Oh are they?
In the Jones case held that you know Clinton could be sued
at as he was sitting
while he was a sitting president. While he was a sitting president.
Right but that's okay, so that's being דן ודנין אותו, dan vedanin
oso, but how about מעיד ומעידין עליו? me'id ume'idin alav? Right, if
we had a court case that was involving the Clinton land deal
going back a few years or whatever, right, could I bring a
sitting president to be a witness in our civil dispute? I don't
think so. Anyway, okay, לא מעיד ולא מעידין אותו. lo me'id velo
me'idin oso. לא חולץ Lo choletz now we're going to deal with
the חליצה chalitza issue. לא חולץ ולא חולצין לאשתו. lo choletz velo
choltzin leishto. He does not do חליצה, chalitza, which would have the
woman spitting at him, and if he dies, חליצה chalitza is not
done to his wife, which is that's
interesting. לא מיבם, Lo meyabem, he doesn't do יבום yibum to his
brother's wife, ולא מיבמין לאשתו, velo meyabemin leishto, if he dies יבום
yibum is not done with his wife. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, אם רצה לחלוץ או ליבם זכור לטוב. im ratza lachlotz o
leyabem zachur letov. If he wants to, then he will be blessed,
meaning maybe we don't submit him to it because it's seen as
demeaning but we obviously it would be a good thing for him
to do it, which suggests by the way that according to the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, if he's not doing חליצה chalitza or יבום,
yibum, his wife remains an עגונה. agunah. Right, so that's deeply troubling
too. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, no, אין שומעין
לו, ein shomin lo, you don't allow him even if he wants.
שמחל על כבודו אין כבודו מחול. Shemachal Al Kevodo, Ein Kevodo Machul.
Even if he wants to waive his honor, that, you know, his
honor represents the nation's honor, and therefore you don't allow him to
do that. ואין נושאין אלמנתו. Ve'ein nosin almanaso. Now, forget Yibum, if
he dies, you're not allowed to marry his widow, because that's what
you see in Tanach, right? That the king's widows were like off-limits
to everybody else. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, נושא המלך אלמנתו
של מלך. Nosei Hamelech Almanaso Shel Melech. A king can marry the
widow of a previous king, assuming that it's not, let's say, his
mother or something, if it's a hereditary position. שכן מצינו בדוד שנשא
אלמנתו של שאול. Sheken matzinu beDavid shenasa almanaso shel Shaul. David married
Saul's widow, שנאמר, Shene'emar, ואתנה לך את בית אדוניך ואת נשי אדוניך
בחיקך. Va'etnah lecha et beit adonecha ve'et neshei adonecha becheikecha. Okay, so
that actually is reflected certain realities in Tanach. So a lot of
interesting things here that are a little off-topic of Sanhedrin, but quite
fascinating. Okay, so let's take a look at the Gemara.
כהן גדול דן, Kohen Gadol dan, Kohen Gadol can be on a
Beis Din. פשיטא, Pshita, of course! Why shouldn't he be on a
Beis Din? I mean, a king won't be on a Beis Din,
so maybe you would have thought it's similar. But anyway, ודנין אותו
Vedanin oto איצטריכא. itztricha. No, you need it for the case to
tell me that he himself can be judged. So הא נמי פשיטא,
ha nami pshita, that's also obvious. אי לא דיינינן ליה, Ei lo
dayninan lei, אי איהו היכי דיין? ei ihu heichi dayan? If we're
not going to allow him to be judged, of course, he himself
can be judged. Why? Because
the verse says והכתיב, Vehaktiv, the verse says, התקוששו וקושו. Hitkosheshu Vakoshu.
Okay, which basically like whatever that means in the original pasuk, the
famous, it's so funny, I know that pasuk from the Gemara, so
I know much more the Gemara's drasha on that, you'd have to
look up what the actual translation is. But אמר ריש לקיש, Amar
Resh Lakish, the Gemara's translation is that from the word like קשוט,
kshot, not the double shin, but as reading it התקוששו hitkosheshu and
the התפעל. hitpa'el. So קשוט kshot is like קישוטין kishutin is like
beautify. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Resh Lakish, קשוט עצמך, kshot atzmecha, so
the first is the התפעל, hitpa'el, beautify yourself, ואחר כך קשוט אחרים,
ve'achar kach kshot acherim, and then beautify others. So you know, like
what is it? A sort of like a reverse of מום שבך
אל תאמר לחברך, mum shebach al tomar lachavercha, if you have your
blemish, don't, you know, don't say it to somebody else, but like
what is also a... what is that line? It's from, there's also
a line from the
gospels, isn't it something about like,
first remove the beam from your eye before you criticize the moat
in your neighbor's eye? But there's something else that's more in the
positive, which is, I don't know, like you know. Anyway, first majorly
improve yourself before you go around trying to improve other people. So
here it's being used in a very powerful way, which is like
look, it's also you know like by Yom Kippur, you know the
Kohen Gadol has to first atone for himself before he atones for
the people. You cannot be in a position to be judging other
people unless you yourself are open to being judged. Here it literally
here would mean until you've been judged yourself. But if you see
yourself, if you're able to be safe, not being able to be
out... if you're outside the law and can't be judged by the
law, if you're not, so then how can you be in the
position to judge other people? Okay, so very sort of a powerful
ethics here that right you cannot judge others. You know, oh that's
the one I was thinking about. What is it? Don't judge others
lest you be judged yourself or something like that? Okay, so here
it's a little bit of the reverse. Before you judge
others you have to be open to being judged yourself and work
obviously on yourself first. So obviously if he's going to judge of
course he can be judged by others. אלא איידי דקבעי למיתני Ella
aidi dikba'ei lemitni מלך לא דן. melech lo dan. Okay
fine, so it's true, they sort of go together. But since we're
going to say a king can't judge ולא דנין אותו velo danin
oto and he can't be judged, so תנא נמי tana nami כהן
גדול דן ודנין אותו. Kohen Gadol dan vedanin oto. So we say
both by a Kohen Gadol. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, הא קמשמע לן,
ha kamashma lan, if you want I'll tell you here's what it's
teaching you, כדתניא, kedetanya, like we've done a baraita: כהן גדול שהרג
את הנפש, Kohen Gadol sheharag et hanefesh, במזיד
נהרג, bemezid neherag, בשוגג גולה. beshogeg goleh. If a Kohen Gadol were
to kill somebody, so if he did it willingly he would be
judged and he would be executed, and if he did it unintentionally
then he would be sent into exile. ועובר על עשה ועל לא
תעשה. Ve'over al asei ve'al lo ta'aseh. He transgresses a positive and
a negative command, which is like what? What do you mean? The
command against murder? What does that mean exactly? We'll see about that,
the Gemara's going to unpack this. והרי הוא כהדיוט לכל דבריו. Vaharei
hu kehedyot lechol devarav. And he's basically treated... there's no special treatment,
he's treated like a commoner. Now, now we're going to unpack what
this means. במזיד נהרג פשיטא. Bemezid neherag pshita. Of course if he
killed במזיד bemezid he'll be
executed once you say that he's judged, right? That goes with that.
בשוגג גולה איצטריכא ליה. Beshogeg goleh itztricha lei. And the chiddush here
is that he's sent into exile if he does it unintentionally. הא
נמי פשיטא. Ha nami pshita. Why not? Isn't that obvious? No, איצטריכא,
itztricha, I need you tell me that. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka datach
amina, I would have thought, הואיל וכתיב, ho'il vechativ, וישב בה עד
מות הכהן הגדול. veyashav bah ad mot hakohen hagadol. The whole point
about being sent into exile is until the Kohen Gadol dies. Okay,
so כל דאית
ליה תקנתא בחזרה לגלות, kol de'it lei takanta bachazara lighlot, I would
say כל דאית ליה תקנתא בחזרה לגלות, kol de'it lei takanta bachazara
lighlot, those that have a fix to come back, he exiles. וכל
דלית ליה תקנתא בחזרה לא לגלות. vechol deleit lei takanta bachazara lo
lighlot. So the problem here is not just that there was he
that the problem here is is that when the Kohen Gadol dies
he'll be dead. So being that he is the Kohen Gadol so
he'll never be able to be free.
So that's the interesting thing, is that it seems from this that
they wouldn't, he would be a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in exile,
but they wouldn't appoint another כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Now, we'll see,
there might be a case where they would appoint another כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, and maybe the point is that when you go into
exile, maybe the other כהן גדול Kohen Gadol hasn't been appointed yet.
So we'll see about that in a minute. But the simple sense
here is, and that's a really interesting question: can somebody serve as
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, right, you know, after having committed murder?
At least unintentionally. So it sounds like here that that he would
remain a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so therefore I would say
don't go into גלות Golus because there's no opportunity of being freed.
לא ליגלי lo ligli דתנן, detnan, where do we see this idea
elsewhere? Because we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, ההורג כהן גדול ha-horeig
Kohen Gadol beginning of י"ח ע"ב, yod-chet amud-bet, ההורג כהן גדול ha-horeig
Kohen Gadol או o כהן גדול שהרג את הנפש, Kohen Gadol she-harag
et ha-nefesh, so if somebody kills a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol committed murder, אינו יוצא משם לעולם. eino
yotzei misham le-olam. So he would be there forever. Now why is
the one who killed a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol there forever? So
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, ההורג כהן גדול
בשוגג גולה לעיר מקלט ואינו יוצא משם לעולם דכיון דאין כהן גדול
במקדש כשהוא גולה במיתת
מי ישוב. ha-horeig Kohen Gadol bishogeg, goleh le-ir miklat, ve-eino yotzei misham
le-olam, dekivan de-ein Kohen Gadol be-mikdash keshe-hu goleh, bemisas mi yashuv. Since
when he went into exile there was no כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
then there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that defines his tenure in
exile, even if one is appointed later, and therefore there's no death
of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that can free him. Okay, וכן
כהן גדול שהרג את הנפש בשוגג במיתת מי ישוב הלך לו כהן
גדול. ve-khen Kohen Gadol she-harag et ha-nefesh bishogeg, bemisas mi yashuv? Halekha
Kohen Gadol. So notice the difference in רש"י. Rashi. In the first
case he says there was no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that had
yet been appointed. And without a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who is
in their position when the person was exiled, his freedom is defined
by the death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who was in
that position when he was sent into exile. So in the first
case, the person who killed the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, there was
no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in that role when he was sent
into exile, so there's nobody whose death can free him. Okay, but
in the second case, even after the guy committed murder, he's still
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the only problem is not that
there was nobody in that position, the only problem was was that
he there's no death that will free him because it's his own
death that we're talking about. Okay, that sounds to be. Now תוספות
Tosafot points out that once that's the problem, you could have an
exception to it, certainly in the first case. If you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, אינו יוצא משם לעולם פירוש כגון שלא מינו אחר עד
שנגמר דינו. eino yotzei misham le-olam, perush kegon she-lo minu acher ad
she-nigmar dino. Okay, so that would only be if in the presumably
in the first case where the guy killed the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, that they did not appoint another one before he was sent
into exile. If they had appointed a substitute, you know, a new
one before he was sent into exile, then that would be the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who would free him. Okay, and then he
says now by the way it's also interesting, it's not limited to
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, there are other people that are pseudo-כהנים
גדולים Kohanim Gedolim that also could free the person. He
says, he says וכגון דליכא משוח שעבר וליכא משוח מלחמה דמשוח שעבר
מחזיר את הרוצח כדברי הכל. u-khegon de-lekam mashuach she-avar ve-lekam mashuach milchama,
ha-mashuach she-avar machzir et ha-rotzeach ke-divrei hakol. So there are different types
of like a person who had been כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in
the past, but had left the position, or somebody who had been
a משוח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, so there might be other people that
could also serve as a type of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
But anyway, so somebody who killed the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doesn't
go into exile, doesn't get freed because there was no כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol in the position when he was sent into exile. And
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol himself, it certainly sounds like here,
would remain the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and therefore, you know, he
would not be freed. Okay, although again I admit that the רש"י
Rashi is a little vague, because רש"י Rashi says במיתת מי ישוב
הלך לו כהן גדול. bemisas mi yashuv? Halekha Kohen Gadol. He doesn't
say במיתת מי ישוב bemisas mi yashuv because he himself is the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So I it's not exactly clear in the
case of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who commits murder whether whether
they would appoint another one in his place or not. Okay, you
could read it either way. You could read it that they wouldn't
and there's got to be an answer to that question, I just
didn't look it up, you know. But you could read it that
they wouldn't and that therefore there's nobody's death who will free him
because it's his own death we're talking about. Or you could read
it like the previous case, that we obviously have to appoint a
new כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, we haven't done it yet, and therefore
there's nobody's death who can free him. Yes?
But if the test is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in office
at the time he was exiled, then even if you did appoint
a substitute, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who did the murder was
in office?
No, but it's not the time that the crime was committed, it's
at the time that the that the judgment was handed down. So
if you imagine that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who committed murder
would be would be sort of, you know, put out of office,
right, so then at the time it could be that, you know,
he was put out of off—well, although it is a little circular,
why would they have put him out of office until after the
judgment was concluded? I think that I'm pretty positive, I think it's
actually pretty explicit, I'm just not remembering, but that a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is, you know, does remain in his position even when
he's sent into exile. So I think
that's
certainly the פשט pshat here. Okay. What about on יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? Okay, אימא לא ליגלי, Eima lo liglei, so anyway, so because
of that, so the actual הלכה halacha is he's in exile and
he's never freed. But I might think that somebody who never has
an opportunity to be freed shouldn't go into גלות, galus, קא משמע
לן, ka mashma lan,
okay, that he does. ואימא הכי נמי, Ve'eima hachi nami, maybe that
is what we should say, that he doesn't go into exile? So
אמר קרא, amar kra, ונס שמה כל רוצח, venas shama kol rotzeiach,
every murderer goes there, אפילו כהן גדול במשמע, afilu Kohen Gadol bemashma,
even the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so that's one thing the
ברייתא braisa teaches, that he goes into exile.
Now, עובר על עשה ועל לא תעשה, over al asei ve'al lo
ta'asei, this כהן גדול Kohen Gadol transgresses a positive and a negative
commandment. What does that mean? לא סגי דלא עבר? Lo sagi dela
avar? What does it mean? If you're a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
you have to transgress a positive and negative command? So no, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, אם עבר על עשה ועל לא תעשה, im avar
al asei ve'al lo ta'asei, הרי
הוא כהדיוט לכל דבריו, harei hu kehediot lechol devarav, like the second
part, after it said he transgresses a positive or negative, it says
and he's like a commoner. So what it means is for any
normal עבירה aveira this guy does, he's treated as a commoner. So
if he commits murder, he's sent to exile or he's executed. If
he commits some normal crime, transgresses some positive מצוה mitzvah or a
negative one and should get מלקות, malkus, he's just treated as a
commoner. פשיטא, Pshita, now, what does that mean? Presumably, it means that
you, well, what we used from the last part, you remember that
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol gets a בית דין Beis Din of
שבעים ואחד. shivim ve'echad. So the question is what type of thing
gives him a בית דין Beis Din of שבעים ואחד? shivim ve'echad?
Is it only capital crimes? What about civil crimes? What about, I
mean, not civil crimes, what about civil acts? What about what about
מלקות? malkus? What type of a בית דין Beis Din would he
get? So this is sort of saying that sounds like, you know,
for normal things that are not capital crimes, he's a commoner, he
gets a בית דין Beis Din of three. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא, pshita, isn't that obvious? סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, הוה דתנן, hava ditnan, אין דנין לא
את השבט ולא את נביא השקר ולא את כהן גדול אלא על
פי בית דין של שבעים ואחד, ein danin lo es hashevet velo
es navi hasheker velo es Kohen Gadol ela al pi Beis Din
shel shivim ve'echad, that you need a בית דין Beis Din of
שבעים ואחד shivim ve'echad normally for a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, ואמר
רבא בר בר חנה, ve'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, כל הדבר הגדול
יביאו אליך, kol hadavar hagadol yavi'u eilecha, דברו של גדול, devaro shel
gadol, all matters that relate to this great personage. So אימא כל
דברו של גדול, eima kol devaro shel gadol, all matters, even monetary,
even מלקות, malkus, whatever. So כל דברו של גדול קא משמע לן.
kol devaro shel gadol ka mashma lan. So this is teaching you
that no, that if it's not a capital crime, he only is
gives a normal בית דין Beis Din of three, he's a total
commoner. ואימא הכי נמי, Ve'eima hachi nami, why don't I say actually
that is true? מי כתיב דברי גדול, Mi kesiv divrei gadol, matters,
meaning all matters? הדבר הגדול כתיב, Hadavar hagadol kesiv, the matter of
the great one, so meaning that things that are very important or
things that relate directly to the person himself. כתיב דבר גדול ממש,
Kesiv davar gadol mamash, it has to not only be a matter
of a great person, but it has to be a great matter
as well, and therefore only a capital crime. And the גמרא Gemara
earlier asked the question about well, whether his שור הנסקל shor haniskal
would get שבעים ואחד, shivim ve'echad, okay, but the גמרא Gemara here
is assuming that really it's only for capital crimes. I should say
even though I said that whatever, we're not going to get a
chance to see ירושלמי Yerushalmi today, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says
that things that are not capital crimes for a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol gets a בית דין Beis Din of עשרים ושלשה. esrim ushlosha.
So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually does not say that he's a commoner
in all matters other than capital crimes. It actually says, you know,
even though it's not the same, he does get a different type
of a בית דין, Beis Din, he still is a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Okay.
So now, okay, so that was all that ברייתא braisa was brought
to, what do you
call, to what was the point of that ברייתא? braisa? Oh, that
was in the discussion of דן ודנין אותו, dan vedanin oso, we
wanted to, although it's not clear, right, what was the question? The
question was why do you have to say, oh, I guess the
point is why did you have to say דנין אותו danin oso
once you said דן, dan, and the answer presumably would be to
tell you, although it didn't tell you it, but implicitly is some
of the stuff that's in this ברייתא. braisa. Number one, that you
would be נידון nidon even in a case of שוגג, shogeg, and
presumably number two, that he would be judged like a commoner when
it was not a capital crime. Okay, so that's included in the
word that he is
דנין אותו. danin oso. Okay. Now, מעיד ומעידין אותו, meid ume'idin oso,
he would testify and you could testify against him. מעיד, Meid, he
could testify, והתניא, vehatanya, והתעלמת מהם, vehisalamta meihem, פעמים שאתה מתעלם ופעמים
שאי אתה מתעלם. pa'amim she'ata misalem ufa'amim she'ei ata misalem. We know
there are actually times where because of a principle of כבוד הבריות,
kevod habriyos, that you actually can passively not perform certain מצוות, mitzvos,
not transgress negative מצוות mitzvos but not perform certain מצוות. mitzvos. And
the basic example, the or the sort of the the basis for
this, the model for this is is the case of returning an
אבידה. aveida. Because it says how can you, you know, do not
see your friend's ox or sheep or whatever and hide yourself from
it, השב תשיבם לאחיך. hashev teshivem le'achicha. So the so it says
לא תראה את שור אחיך או את שיו נדחים והתעלמת מהם, lo
tireh es shor achicha o es seyo nidachim vehisalamta meihem, don't see
it and hide yourself from it. The Rabbis in their great way
bracket the לא lo part of the פסוק pasuk and they basically
say והתעלמת מהם, vehisalamta meihem,
there are times you're supposed to pretend like you didn't
see. What are those times? When it is not befitting your dignity.
When it would be a,
not just like, not just like, oh it's going to take my
time whatever, but it's actually something that would be a compromise of
your dignity. And that becomes a principle that for כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot you can override first of all rabbinic matters and even like
this case of the אבידה, aveidah, even possible biblical matters at least
if it's the passive non-performance of a positive מצווה. mitzvah. So the
גמרא Gemara understands that testifying is a positive obligation to testify. So
but if it's beneath your dignity maybe you shouldn't have to do
it. And maybe you'll say oh but it'll cause a person a
loss of money, not returning their אבידה aveidah also causes them a
loss of money and you're allowed to passively not return. Now maybe
if it's a capital crime we should think about it differently, but
at least this is the question of the גמרא. Gemara. You had
a question, Michal? No? Okay, so it says פעמים שאתה מתעלם ופעמים
שאי אתה מתעלם. peamim sheatah mitalem upeamim she-i ata mitalem. There are
times that you have to sort of hide yourself. היכי דמי? heichi
dami? How is this the case? כהן והוא בבית הקברות. Kohen vehu
beveit hakevarot.
So how about first of all if returning it would cause you
to transgress, there is a כהן Kohen and the אבידה aveidah is
in a
cemetery? Or זקן ואינו לפי כבודו, zaken ve-eino lefi kevodo, this is
what's more relevant for us, you are an elder and to stoop
down and search around and go knocking on doors it would not
be befitting your dignity. או שהיתה מלאכתו מרובה משל חברו o shehayetah
melachto merubah mishel chaveiro or here because it's a monetary issue, even
if it just means that it's going to be cost your time
away from your job is going to be more than this אבידה
aveidah is worth. Now partly about in terms of appreciating that doesn't
just mean that you can always just say, oh it's going to
cost me too much to do this מצווה, mitzvah, right, but that
it's but that like first of all, why should I care if
Hanan's going to lose out $100 if I don't return his object,
but I'm going to lose out $200 in returning it? So this
is a very important principle in all מצוות בין אדם לחברו, mitzvot
bein adam lachaveiro, which is חייך וחיי אחיך חייך קודמים, chayecha vechayei
achicha chayecha kodmim, which is not just about life, but like my
primary obligation is to myself. And it's interesting, that's a core principle
about Jewish ethical obligations, right, that our, it doesn't mean that my
desires come before your needs, but it does mean that my needs
come before your needs. My primary obligation is to myself. So why
is protecting your $100 more important than protecting my
$100 or certainly my $200? So I have a prior obligation to
return my own אבידה aveidah as it were than to return yours.
Let's say there were two אבידות aveidot there, right, one of and
I had to pick one, so I'd be entitled to save my
own אבידה aveidah before saving yours. So if it's going to cost
me more money to return yours than it's worth, my obligation is
to myself first. That's besides even realizing that when I return Hanan's
אבידה aveidah I can tell him, oh by the way, you have
to pay me for the time it took me to return it.
Not that you pay me for the good deed, but you pay
me for the time I took off of work. So if he's
going to have to shell out that $200, it's not going to
be worth it for him either for me to return the אבידה.
aveidah. So in that type of a case you're exempt from returning
it. Okay, וכן נאמר והתעלמת מהם. vechen neemar vehitalamta mehem. Therefore it
says that you should hide yourself from them.
He also said returning it, right,
it doesn't mean that it won't get returned, but there could be
a scenario where even that's true. Like it's about to get crushed
or something, or whatever it might be. If I don't jump into
the ocean right now and save it, it's going to get washed
away. And nevertheless, I don't have to worry about that if I
have if my if protecting my own property, that has a that
comes first.
Okay, so, okay, so, you
could if you want to. It's an important principle, I don't know,
it's a little off topic but I'll just say it, you see,
now that we're not doing the ירושלמי Yerushalmi today, I have more
time to talk about things, so, which could be an interesting question
in general whether we should be doing the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. But anyway,
I'll just mention this because it's just so important and it just
just came up recently in a rabbinic listserv that I'm part of,
is a question about כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av va-em when you're
dealing with like abusive parents. And even if we're talking about like
not physically abusive, just verbally abusive, in ways in which doing the
מצווה mitzvah of כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av va-em comes at a
great emotional
distress and psychic sort of cost to the person. So some people
try to say, oh you're פטור patur because in that case the
parent is a רשע rasha and you're פטור patur in case of
רשע. rasha. Like I don't like that approach at all. First of
all because רשע rasha is used to traditionally to exclude somebody who's
like not שומר מצוות. shomer mitzvot. So we're going to start saying
that if your parents aren't שומר מצוות shomer mitzvot you're not חייב?
chayav? And also like just because there's cases like about people acting
horribly or unethically doesn't mean that you make a whole statement that
the person is a רשע. rasha. But the real reason why a
person is exempt in that case is for this principle, that your
prior obligation is to yourself. And this is even true, like everybody's
brought up with these stories about the mother who rips the clothes
off the son and he doesn't embarrass her or throws the wallet
in the ocean and he doesn't react. So the פוסקים poskim say
that that's only after the fact you can't react. But if you
had to to protect yourself from being shamed in public or to
protect your money from being destroyed, had to actually prevent your parents
from doing that and actually so that would be... actually your responsibility
to yourself comes prior to your obligation of כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud
Av V'eim. So people don't know that, sadly, and that's really, really
important, and that's just part of a general principle that in בין
אדם לחברו, bein adam l'chavero, you know, you have a prior obligation
to yourself. So sadly that message is often lost, but it's really
critical. Anyways, so that's this issue about returning the אבידה. aveidah. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, anyway, so why does a king get—why
does a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol have to testify? Isn't that beneath
his dignity? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יוסף—no, Amar Rav
Yosef
he can testify to a king, that wouldn't be beneath his dignity
if it was a court case that involved a king. Okay, does
it mean against a king? Does it mean to defend a king?
Okay, maybe it means to defend a king. Okay, but anyway והתנן—one
V'hatnan minute the גמרא Gemara says, how does a king get into
a court case? Didn't our משנה Mishna say לא דן ולא דנין
אותו—a Lo dan v'lo danin oso king is not part—is not judged,
לא מעיד ולא מעידין אותו—and Lo meid v'lo meidin oso you don't
testify against him or maybe even it means for him.
I misread that. He doesn't testify, but anyway, but he's not judged
also.
He's—he doesn't testify and he's not testified against. So anyway, so how
does he get into being a court case and how would a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol be a witness for him? אלא אמר רב
זירא Ela amar Rav Zeira מעיד לבן מלך. meid l'ben melech. Okay,
okay, the prince. Okay, the king's son is in the court case.
But that at least would be befitting the כהן גדול'ס Kohen Gadol's
dignity and that's why he would have to show up as a
witness. So the גמרא Gemara says בן מלך הדיוט הוא. Ben melech
hedyot hu. This is a fascinating—ah, so what? He's the son of
a king? He's just a commoner! Which is a fascinating idea, right?
Like the גמרא Gemara doesn't have a halakhic status of a prince.
There's a reality that you might be the next one in line
to being king, okay, but there's no like halakhic status, and somehow
because there's no halakhic status, we can't say that it's befitting the
כהן גדול'ס Kohen Gadol's dignity, which is bizarre since this is an
issue of כבוד kavod and dignity and so on, who needs the
person to have a status? If he's a prince, you know, but
then maybe it is befitting my status to come to testify in
a case involving a prince. But I don't know. Okay, so it
says
הדיוט הוא. hedyot hu. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא מעיד בפני המלך. Ela meid bifnei hamelech. Okay,
it means that fine, it's not the king is a litigant, but
it's the court case is being held in the presence of the
king. Now of course that's also a problem because that sounds like
the king is a judge, but we said that kings are not
judges. So the גמרא Gemara is going to—we're going to see what
it sort of seems to me by this and where it's going,
is this idea he's not technically a judge, but the case is
being held in his presence. You know, you could sort of imagine
that, right? That the king is sort of sitting in the court—it's
taking place in his presence and he's sort of sitting over the
court, not formally in any role of a judge, but like sort
of, you know, supervising the proceedings. And that would be appropriate for
him to appear as a כהן. Kohen. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואין מושיבין מלך בסנהדרין. V'ein moshivin melech b'Sanhedrin. So,
but you don't have a king in the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Now the
way—now the reason it didn't say ואין דנין, v'ein danin, the king
doesn't judge, seems to be because it understands that we're not talking
about him serving technically as a judge. We're talking about him sort
of just being there in a position of authority without technically being
a judge. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, but you wouldn't do
that either, right? Because it would completely like, you know, like skew
the, you know, objectivity of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Separation of powers.
Exactly. And separation of powers. So משום יקרא דכהן גדול, mishum yikra
d'Kohen Gadol, no, it could have been, it would be in this
case because we have to have a case where would a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol testify that it would be the honor of a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so we're still imagining that you—it seems
like we're still imagining that his son is still being—this is the
way the רש"י Rashi explains it, his son is still being judged,
okay? Whether his son is being, I don't know, it's whether it's
a civil case or a criminal case. So because his son is
being judged, the king comes to preside over the—over the, you know,
proceedings. Okay, so much for sort of not skewing the proceedings. And
because the king is present, even though he's not technically sitting on
the court case, okay, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is within his
honor to come testify. So it says משום יקרא דכהן גדול אתא
ויתיב—so mishum yikra d'Kohen Gadol asa v'yasiv because of to give honor
to the—because of the honor of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the
king would come and sit. He wouldn't be present ongoing, that would
be inappropriate, but we needed the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to appear,
so we asked the king to come so it would be within
the honor of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to appear. And it's
the king's son who's part of the case, so therefore the king
shows up. Okay? משום יקרא דכהן גדול אתא ויתיב—because mishum yikra d'Kohen
Gadol asa v'yasiv the honor of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the
king comes and sits—מקבלי מיניה
סהדותא—and mekabli minei sahadusa therefore we accept the testimony of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol because we made it now befitting of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol to appear—קאי
ואזיל—and kai v'azil then the king goes after he was just present
in order to receive—for the moment where the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
had to appear and testify. And then he leaves, okay, to allow
the court to restore its objective deliberations. ומשקלי ומתרינן בדינא. u'mashkali u'matrinan
b'dina. And we will then engage in the deliberations. So it sort
of says you might have him there in a very sort of
pro... forma appearance in order to allow the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
to come and appear. But the basic effect of this whole discussion
is that the גמרא Gemara basically has made moot the point that
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would testify. It's basically said the only
time a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would testify would be in a
very rare exceptional type of a case where it would be with
befitting his dignity. But otherwise actually you would not be able to
be called to, or he could refuse to come because it is
beneath his dignity. Alright, so that's very interest—interesting.
Next, גופא, gufa, let's go look at what we said before. אין
מושיבין מלך בסנהדרין, ein moshivin melech b'Sanhedrin, you don't have a king
in a סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Again, presumably that means not only does he
not judge, but he doesn't even—he's not even there playing some type
of a, you know, presiding role. Okay, ולא מלך וכהן גדול בעיבור
שנה, v'lo melech v'Kohen Gadol b'ibur shana, and you don't have a
king or a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol part of the בית דין
beis din to determine whether to make it a leap year or
not. Now, מלך בסנהדרין, melech b'Sanhedrin, דכתיב, d'ksiv, לא תענה על ריב,
lo sa'aneh al riv, do not respond on a debate or whatever,
לא תענה על רב, lo sa'aneh al rav, that you can't respond
once a—a greater authority has spoken, which is why if you know
like by דיני נפשות dinei nefashos they start from the sort of
smaller authorities so that people will be free to debate it. So
you can't have a king there because that will silence everybody else.
Okay, so that's why he can't be on the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, presumably
again it means even in just like—you know, even in a sort
of non-judging position, just to sort of be part of the deliberations
or whatever. No, that's going to not allow for an open and
honest debate, so he can't be on it.
Now, לא מלך וכהן גדול בעיבור שנה, lo melech v'Kohen Gadol b'ibur
shana, now they can't be part of the עיבור שנה. ibur shana.
Why not?
מלך משום אפסניא, melech mishum afsanya, or which presumably means if Charlie
was here he would tell us what the Greek word meant, but
basically it means the money that they spend on their troops and
so on. So if there's an extra month in the year, presumably
they paid an annual salary. So anybody who's paying an annual salary
really wants there to be a leap year, because you get an
extra month of labor out of your people. What does it say
the Greek word—does it say what the Greek word is? No, it
says wages. Wages. Yeah, whatever. Anyway, it says wages for his troops,
so he would actually get an extra month out of all the
people that work for the federal government—a free month of labor. כהן
גדול משום צינה, Kohen Gadol mishum tzina, because of cold. So רש״י
Rashi says the cold concern is that it'll be cold when it's
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and therefore you'll have to—what do you call
it? You know, and he's going to have to dunk five times
or whatever. So he'd rather it not be a cold month, and
that's not fair to everybody else, that's not necessarily a good judgment
on behalf of everybody else. תוספות Tosafot says no no no, they
would heat up the מקוה. mikvah. So תוספות Tosafot says the cold
would be that the floor of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would
be cold and he has to do it barefoot. But anyway, but
that's all very, you know, that's all very like self-interest and not
doing it on behalf of the people. Okay, so which is how
the decision should be made. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, שמע
מינה, shma mina, we can infer from this discussion that שתא בתר
ירחא אזלא, shata basar yarcha azla, the year goes by the months.
Now that's not exactly clear what that means, because what—you know, I'll
just say it the way תוספות Tosafot says what that means is,
when you are
determining—תוספות Tosafot says—at least I don't really understand רש״י, Rashi, I mean
whatever תוספות Tosafot doesn't understand רש״י Rashi either. But when you're determining
to make the year and to make it an עיבור ibur year,
we had these discussions in the first פרק. perek. Remember we discussed
two things, תקופה tkufa and אביב? aviv? And remember what the difference
was? אביב Aviv was agriculturally what's actually happening. תקופה Tkufa is where's—where's
the sun? You know, and so now normally those would be aligned,
but not necessarily. Okay, so he's saying since you just discussed their
reasons, or the reason of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was that
it be too cold, it sounds like the issue of the year
is determined by the issue of cold versus hot. And that's sort
of how you're making your חשבון cheshbon of making an עיבור ibur
year, which is like the תקופה, tkufa, as opposed to the question
of what the agricultural realities are. Okay, so he says והנהו תלתא
בקרי, v'hanehu thalasa bakrei, these three shepherd—cowherds, דהוו קיימי ומשתעו, d'hava kaimei
u'mishta'ei,
they were standing and talking, ושמעינהו רבנן, v'shaminhu rabanan, and the rabbis
heard, דקאמרי, d'ka'amrei, and this is what they were saying. חד אמר,
chad amar, one said, אם בכיר ולקיש כחדא ינצו, im bachir v'lakish
k'chada yintzu, if the—if the early grain and the late grain כחדא
ינצו, k'chada yintzu, blossom at the same
time—not blossom, there's gotta be another word—sprout at the same time, דיין
הוא אדר, dain hu Adar, and then this has gotta be the
month of אדר. Adar. ואי לא, v'im lo, and if this doesn't
happen, לית דין אדר, lais dain Adar, then it's not אדר, Adar,
it would be שבט. Shevat. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, and one said,
אם תור בצפר בטלא ימות, im tor b'tzfar b'talla yamut, if—if an
ox in the morning will like, you know, die because of the—of
the—of the snow, like will die because it's so cold if it's
really cold in the morning, ובטיהרא, u'b'tihara, at noon, בטור תאנה ידמוך
ישלח משכיה, b'tor t'eina yidmoch yishlach mashchei, in the shade of a
fig tree... He will sleep and cast off his
skin, he'll be so hot, he'll scrape
up, he'll shed his skin or whatever, got to cool off or
something. Anyway, so it'd be really cold in the morning and really
hot by noon time. So then דיין הוא אדר, dein hu Adar,
and this is אדר. Adar. ואם לאו ליתא אדר, ve'im lav leise
Adar, it's not, it's not yet אדר, Adar, it's still טבת. Tevet.
I mean, excuse me, שבט. Shevat. וחד אמר, vechad amar, and
one said,
אם קידום תקיף לקדא, im kidum takif lekada, if the east wind
is very strong,
יפח בלואך נפיק וכבלי, ye'pach beluach nafika vekivlei, and when you blow
out from your mouth then you could see the breath in front
of you. So דיין הוא אדר, dein hu Adar, then it's אדר,
Adar, ואם לאו ליתא אדר, ve'im lav leise Adar, if it's not,
it's not אדר. Adar. So basically, if you think about it, the
last two were about the question of the heat and the first
one was about the question of the crops. Okay, and because of
these things ועברוה רבנן להשתא, ve'ibruha rabanan le'hashtah, and the Rabbis made
it an intercalary year because they realized, oh, it doesn't really deserve
to be אדר, Adar, it should be שבט. Shevat. We'll have to
add another אדר Adar to turn this אדר Adar effectively into שבט.
Shevat. It's not yet the time for אדר. Adar. So anyway, what
you see is that the year is determined based on the question
not only of heat, but also what the first shepherd said, or
whatever cowherd said, of the question of the agriculture. So don't you
see that that's also part of it? So the גמרא Gemara says
ותסברה רבנן, vetisbera rabanan, does that really make sense that that's what
happened?
רבנן ארוותא סמכי, rabanan arevusa samchi, you think the Rabbis just rely
on shepherds?
אלא רבנן אחשבנייהו סמכי, ela rabanan achushbenayehu samchi, they rely on their
own calculations, and calculations have to do with where is the sun.
Right, what the agricultural state is, is you have to look at
the reality. Calculations is the תקופה. tekufah. For the Rabbis rely on
their determining of the תקופה, tekufah, which is an issue more of
the sun and of the heat, okay. ורועי בקר אשיוחי דאסתייע מילתא,
veroi bakar isyuhi de'istaye milta, and they just added support by the
testimony of the shepherd. So it really is the way תוספות Tosafot
understands this, the question is how much are we rely, is it
a question of the season and the sun, and how much is
it a question about the agricultural realities, and it seems like the
conclusion is that it's primarily about the issue of the sun and
secondarily about those agricultural realities. Okay, so we will end with this.
Okay.